Guide to the Karen M. Offen Papers SC1169
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Karen M. Offen papers
1870-2007
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Offen, Karen.
SC1169
56 megabyte(s)
28.5 Linear Feet (24 boxes)
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical / Historical
Karen Offen is a Senior Scholar with the Michelle R. Clayman Institute for Gender Research at Stanford University. Her research interests include history of Modern Europe, especially France and its global influence; Western thought and politics with reference to family, gender, and the relative status of women; historiography; women's history; the national, regional and global histories of feminism; and comparative history. Offen earned a B.A. in History from the University of Idaho in 1961, and an M.A. (1964) and Ph.D. (1971) in Modern European History from Stanford University.
Scope and Contents
Papers include Offen’s files about K-12 curriculum; people files and correspondence, and research about the birth of the field of Women’s History. Also included documents and letters related to Offen and Bell’s book “Women, the Family, and Freedom: The Debate in Documents.” Accession 2017-022 includes Offen’s dissertation research material on Paul de Cassagnac.
Women in education -- California -- Stanford.; Women historians -- Archives; Women authors.; Women’s studies.; Women -- History -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States.; Women -- United States -- History.; Women -- History -- Study and teaching (Higher); Women -- Education (Higher) -- United States.; Women in education -- United States.; Offen, Karen.; Offen, Karen.; Offen, Karen.; Cassagnac, Paul de, 1843-1904
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2016-112
  - Third Republic/Troisieme Republique (Spring/Fall, #3/4), 1977; 56 megabyte(s)
  - Women, The Family, and Freedom (manuscript), volume I (Box 1)
  - Women, The Family, and Freedom (manuscript), volume II (Box 2)
  - Women, The Family, and Freedom (edited manuscript), volume I (Box 3)
  - Women, The Family, and Freedom (edited manuscript), volume II (Box 4)
  - Cassagnac Research (1 of 3), 1970-1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cassagnac Research (2 of 3), 1970-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cassagnac Research (3 of 3), 1970-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - CV, 1980 Fall (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - CV/Bio, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - CV, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Positions, 1984-1999 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - USF, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Stanford/History/Positions, 1986- (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - History department info, 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Stanford - faculty (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Berkeley UC - Psych studies, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Michigan, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Arizona State (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Mills, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Ohio State, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Unlabeled (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Karen, 1985-1991 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - K (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Karen, 1981-1987 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Survey Questionaire (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Southern Associationfor Women Historians (SAWH), 1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - CCWHP newsletters (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - CCWHP newsletters (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - CCWHP newsletters (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - CCWHP newsletters (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - CCWHP newsletters (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - NRC, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Summary report NRC, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Summary Report AHA (American Historical Association), 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Summary Report Survey of the Historical Profession, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - CWH meeting, 1985 Mar 29 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Agenda committee on Women Historians AHA, 1984 Dec 28 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Committee on Women Historians, 1985 Dec 28 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - CWH Agenda book meeting, 1984 Mar (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - unlabeled (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - AHA - CWH, 1983 Mar (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - AHA - CWH (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Calendar, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Ritual and Performance calendar, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - News on Cossagnac, 1966 Sep (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Cassagnac Family Papers - inventaires (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Cassagnac - illustrations (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Picture Paul de Cassagnac (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Cassagnac Archives (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Cassagnac Obituary - Parisien Press (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Prince Imperial to Paul de Cassagnac (6 pieces) (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - CCWHP newsletters, 1973-1976 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - CCWHP/CGWH Current correspondence, 1971-1977 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - CCWH co-secretary binder (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Unlabeled (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - With newsletters (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - WHOM - Newsleters, 1974-1978 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - CCWHP / correspondence with S. Cooper, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - AHA / CCWHP / ERA, 1978-1980 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Southern Caucus, 1972-1987 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Newsletter pamphlet (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Ch. 8 - Cassagnac (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Ch. 9 - Cassagnac (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Ch. 10 - Cassagnac (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Conclusion: Cassagnac (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Back Matter: Cassagnac illustrations, bibliography (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Unlabeled (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Unlabeled, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - The Political Career of Paul de Cassagnac, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Front Matter: Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Ch. 1 - Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Offen (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Ch. 2 - Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Ch. 3 - Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Ch. 4 - Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Ch. 5 - Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Ch. 6 - Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Ch. 7 - Cassagnac (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Working copy Chapter 7, 1985-1988 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - VW - Second Printing, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - VW - Publicity, 1981-2015 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: VH, 1972-1989 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - VH - Dealings with SU Press, 1978-1980 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - The Female Experience: Victorian Heritage (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - The Female experience: part 2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Part 3: Friendship, Marriage, and Motherhood (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Part 4: work (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Part 4: work (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Victorian Women mss pt. 1 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Victorian Women mss pt. 2 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Victorian Women mss pt. 3 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Victorian Women mss pt. 4 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Sears case, 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Plan for an AHA conf. in women's history/ corresp. (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Joan Kelly Prize (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - E. Freedman case (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Science, Engineering, and Humanities Doctorates in the United States profile, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Higher Education Salary Evaluation Kit (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Survey of the Historical Profession, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Guidelines (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Archive notes. AN APP Cassagnac Gers (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers le Pap, L'Autorde, 1873-1893 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation Research Records (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Index Cards (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Calendar, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Images (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Images (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2017-022
  - Women's History (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - IFUW Conference, 1992 Aug (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Woodside High/ Sequoia Union H.S. District, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Woodside Elementary, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cañada College - In Service, 1993 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - K-12 Misc. Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National Contacts, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - K-12 National Standards Issue (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Curriculum, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Guidelines, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - State of California, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Curriculum, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Industrial Revolution - 10th grade, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Port Royal Experiment (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - California Women, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - History/Social Science Framework, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Crowning the Cathedral of Florence (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Women, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Women (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - K-12 girls, 1985-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National STDs FLAP, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - K-12 pubs (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Framework Revision Initiative, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National History Day (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National History Day (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - History-Social Science Framework (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - AAWW Gender Equity (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - California Commission on the Status of Women (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Corr. With Lynn, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gender (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gender (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous books on Social Studies (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Women East West, CCWH, WAWH, Feminists Europe pubs (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - WFF - Notes for a Re-Edition, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Intitute for Research on Women and Gender - Women, the Family, and Freedom, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - WFF - Sales / Financial (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - WFF - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Permissions (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Offen-Bell Anthology Project, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - WFF - Promotion (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Further Reading (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bibliography WFF (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - WFF (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - ABIR-AM, Pnina G. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - BERNARD-POWERS, Jane (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - BIRNBAUM, Lucia (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - BLACK, Naomi (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - BROWN, Judith (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - BURKHARD "Bud" Fred (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CHAN-TIBERGHIEN, Jennifer (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - CHAPMAN, Herrick (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - COHEN, Bill Indiana U. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - DEGLER, Carl (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - DERFLER, Les (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - FRIEDMAN, Adele C. Berkeley (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - FROST, Rogi (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - GORDON, Bonnie (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - HOLUB, Renate (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - KANNER, Penny (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - KELLER, Frances R., 2007 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Laura X. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - MARAINI, Dacio (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - MCKIBBEN, Carol (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - MIDDLEBROOK, Diane (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - MOHR, Janet (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - MONTGOMERY, Maureen (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - MYERS, Mitzi (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - OWENS, Jack (ISU) (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - ROELKER, Nancy, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - SCHNEIDER, Wm (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - SLAUGHTER, Jane (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - SOH, Sarah (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - AUTUMN, Stanley (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - STOKES, Patty, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - WINTER, Jay (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - TOMBS, Terry (Spain) (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - UNO, Kathy (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - WRIGHT, Gordon (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Older Correspondence, 1982-84-85 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1986-may-dec (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1987-jan-1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1995-97 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Q's Hist. Week (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Integrating Women Into History Project Questionnaire, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - OAH/FIPSE Curriculum Packets (1 of 2 ) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - OAH/FIPSE Curriculum Packets (2 of 2 ) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Women's History Insitute Packets (1 of 2), 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Women's History Insitute Packets (2 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Bibliography: Women in 19th 20th C. Europe (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Women's History - Finding Aids (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Teaching the History of Women, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Women's History Syllabi (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Women's History Syllabi (2 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Female Studies No. 1 by Sheila Tobias (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Female Studies No. 1 by Sheila Tobias (2 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Women's History, Bibliographies, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - OAH/FIPSE Curriculum Packets (1 of 3) (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - OAH/FIPSE Curriculum Packets (2 of 3) (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - OAH/FIPSE Curriculum Packets (3 of 3) (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - KCBS Women's History Month - "In Her Times", 1991 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - GERS (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers, 1945-1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Biog. Information Paul de Cassagnac (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - PC - prior to 1870 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Q's of Mayor Significance (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Appel au Peuple" - project (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Bonapartists (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ante-Rep., 1870's (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Anti-Republican politics, 1880's (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Royalists/Conserv. Alliance (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Socio-Econ. Q. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - J.O. Election, 1878 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Bretevil, Marquis de - Memoires (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Dechamps, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Descotes, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Xeroxes (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Terrien - Mgr. Freppel (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Parliament - Elections Politics (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Journal Officiel Annez Politique - References (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Dissertation - Working Copy (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - To see in France / Cassagnac (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Cassagnac - To Do (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Materials Consulted for PC but not used (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - PC Brook - Proofs, connections (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Dissertation Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Corresp.: Cassagnac (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Oeuvres, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Granier de Cassagnac - father of Paul de Cassagnac (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Orig. Typescript PC 1881-85 paper (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - PC article / 1988 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Articles, 1873-1875 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Archives (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - B. Martin/Albert de Mun, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Duvall/Granier de Cassagnac, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - G.Sourbadere / B. A. Granier de Cassagnac (1 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - G.Sourbadere / B. A. Granier de Cassagnac (2 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 16)